<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles of agreement, concerning the cessation of warre, betweene the Arch-duke and the states of the vnited Prouinces Procured by a fryar, called Iohn of Ney, confessour to the Arch-duke and the Infanta. Wherunto is annexed the state of other things happened about the same time. With Warres testament, or his last will, made at his departure out of the said Netherlauds [sic]. Translated out of the Dutch.</title>
            <title>Treaties, etc. United Provinces of the Netherlands. Staten Generaal, 1607</title>
            <author>Netherlands. Sovereign (1598-1621 : Albert and Isabella).</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 21 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08094</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18455</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113144</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848383</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848383</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13473</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08094)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13473)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 723:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles of agreement, concerning the cessation of warre, betweene the Arch-duke and the states of the vnited Prouinces Procured by a fryar, called Iohn of Ney, confessour to the Arch-duke and the Infanta. Wherunto is annexed the state of other things happened about the same time. With Warres testament, or his last will, made at his departure out of the said Netherlauds [sic]. Translated out of the Dutch.</title>
                  <title>Treaties, etc. United Provinces of the Netherlands. Staten Generaal, 1607</title>
                  <author>Netherlands. Sovereign (1598-1621 : Albert and Isabella).</author>
                  <author>John, of Ney.</author>
                  <author>W. BB.</author>
                  <author>United Provinces of the Netherlands. Staten Generaal. Treaties, etc. Netherlands. Sovereign (1598-1621 : Albert and Isabella), 1607.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By Simon Stafford] for Thomas Archer, and are to be sold at his shop in Popes head Alley, neere the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1607.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translator's preface signed: W.BB.</note>
                  <note>"Warre's testament" is in verse.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1621 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13473:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13473:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ARTICLES OF AGREEMENT, CONCER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Ceſſation of Warre, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Arch-duke and the States of the vnited Prouinces.</p>
            <p>Procured by a Fryar, called <hi>Iohn of Ney,</hi> Confeſſour to the Arch-duke and the <hi>Infanta.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherunto is annexed the ſtate of other things happened about the ſame time.</p>
            <p>With Warres Teſtament, or his laſt Will, made at his departure out of the ſaid Netherlands.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated out of the Dutch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Imprinted at London for <hi>Thomas Archer,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Popes head Alley, neere the Royall Exchange, 1607.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13473:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:13473:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:13473:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13473:3"/>
            <head>Newes to the Reader, or to whom the Buyer deſires to ſend Newes.</head>
            <p>SVch is the time, that when friends congratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, the ſecond word is <hi>what's the newes?</hi> So likewiſe, when our vrgent occaſions re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire conference by letters, yet wee expect with thoſe letters, what Newes; if we come from the Court, what Newes; if we come from the Countrie, what newes: So from whenceſoeuer wee come or goe, what Newes. Therefore for them that deſire newes, eſpecially to you, I preſent theſe Netherland accurrents, lately come to my handes from a worthy friend out of Holland, this <hi>18.</hi> of Iune. <hi>1607.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine</hi> W.B B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:13473:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13473:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Articles of Agreement concerning</hi> the Ceſſation of warre, betweene the Arch-duke and the States of the vnited Prouinces.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou haue heard howe a Fryar, the Confeſſor to the <hi>Infanta,</hi> hath brought about a Ceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Armes for 8. moneths, to the end that in that 8. mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths, theſe States might acquaint their beſt friendes, and counſell themſelues, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they will make a peace or no, vpon rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable termes; in which it is propounded beforehand, that the Arch-duke ſhall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime from all intereſt in them, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
<pb facs="tcp:13473:5"/>ouer theſe Prouinces vnited, that they ſhall, as a free State, treate, and hold all that they now doe, except by conſent, ſome towne or place may be changed, for the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodating of the Arch-duke or this States and that the King of Spaine ſhall, within the terme of three moneths, ſend to the States his agreement to and of the ſame Acte.</p>
            <p>Now vpon this, there hath beene que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion mooued; firſt concerning the word <hi>Inuaſion,</hi> then for the calling home of the Fleet: and what hath beene done in that, I ſend you herewith; and the preſent ſtate of things here.</p>
            <p>Touching the interpretation of that word, it is this concluded; that during the Ceſſation, their Prouinces, Territories, and other particular poſſeſſions on eyther ſide, as well by water as land, ſhal be free from all inuaſion, and all manner of hoſtilitie, by Armie, troope, or partie.</p>
            <p>That in the neutrall Countries adioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, no actions of hoſtilitie ſhall be vſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the inhabitants paſſengers, &amp; others being no ſouldiers, nor againſt horſes, dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of horſes, or thoſe men which ſhal draw
<pb facs="tcp:13473:5"/>ſhippes and boates, on both ſides the riuers.</p>
            <p>That all actions to the contrary, ſhall of all ſides bee hindered, puniſhed and repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: with this prouiſo, that it muſt be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, that ſuch offences committed againſt the Contract, tend not to the violation or breaking of the Ceſſation vnleſſe they bee done by the order and appointment of the King of Spaine or the Arch-duke on the one ſide, or the States on the other.</p>
            <p>That all ſouldiers by land and water, horſe and foot (out of the townes or fortes where they ſerue) as alſo all others, hauing no paſport or reſiding vnder ſafegard, all vnfree goods, and the perſons and goods which ſhall be tranſported from one ſide to the other, without paſport and licence, are excepted out of thoſe limits, and remaine ſubiect to the order and rigour of the warre.</p>
            <p>That the Contribution on eyther ſide (during the Ceſſation) ſhalbe raiſed &amp; exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, as they were at the day of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of Ceſſation, (namely the 12. of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prill laſt) without enhauncement, and at the perill of thoſe that ſhall execute the ſame.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:13473:6"/>
               <head>Touching Ceſſation of Armes at Sea.</head>
               <p>THe States haue agreed to call home their Fleete from the coaſt of Spaine, with their firſt meanes after the King of Spaines declaration, agreeable to that of his Highneſſes, which ſhall (according to promiſe) be deliuered vnto them; and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time limitted for the ſaid deliuerie, (whereof there is yet ſeuen weeks or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts to come) not to re'nforce their ſayd Fleete.</p>
               <p>That when 6. weekes are expired, after the ſaid deliuerie, all prizes (except ſhips of warre and ſouldiers) which ſhall be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken on the ſea, from the Gorlings ſouth and towards the weſt, along the coaſt of France, Spaine and Barbary, and in the Straight of Giberalter, and in the Midland ſea, ſhall be held for vnlawful Prize, and reſtorde.</p>
               <p>That all Prizes on either part (except ſhippes of warre and ſouldiers) which ſhall bee taken on the north ſeas, or on the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row ſeas, betweene great Brittaine and France, as farre as the Gorlings, after the fourteenth of Iune (after their computa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion)
<pb facs="tcp:13473:6"/>ſhall be held for vnlawfull prize, and reſtorde.</p>
               <p>And thoſe Articles of Ceſſation to be of force during that limit.</p>
               <p>Prouided, that the order preſently obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the States, againſt the going out and into the hauens of Flaunders, ſhall remaine lawfull for the States to execute, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Ceſſation; granted onely to the Arch-duke, that they ſhall ſuffer his ſmall Fiſherie without the hauens, during the Ceſſation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>I Muſt giue you likewiſe the Report of a Fight at Sea, betweene the ſhipping of Spaine and the States.</p>
               <p>On the 15. of Aprill, 1607. the States Fleete being 29. ſhippes of warre, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion, arriued in the Bay of Giberalter, where they found the Armado of Spaine, about 12. or 13. ſhips of warre, (beſides ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen or eight Marchants) who had order to hale on the Hollanders, going in or out
<pb facs="tcp:13473:7"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13473:7"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13473:8"/>the ſtraights. The States ſhippes reſolued with order and courage, to attempt the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, as they lay in the Road, vnder the ſhot of the Towne and Caſtell. The Admirall with another good ſhippe, commanded by Captaine <hi>Lambrecht,</hi> boarded the Spaniſh Admirall with full ſayle, and beat her ſo violently with ordinance and musket, that in a ſhort ſpace ſhe loſt her Generall, with almoſt 300. men, being a ſhip of 400. laſt or burthen, manned with 500. and carrying 21. great braſſe peeces.</p>
               <p>After fiue houres fight, the States had the victorie, but with danger: for fire happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in the Spaniſh Viceadmirall, when ſhe was grappled, the States ſhippes had much adoe to ſaue themſelues from burning. The Spaniſh Admirall with ſome others ran a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ground, ſuffred the fire to lay hold on them, and increaſed it, to preuent the States profit by taking them. The next day examining the ſucceſſe, they left (of the 21. ſhippes which they found in the Bay at their ariual) but two Gallions, one French ſhip, and a ſmall pinnaſſe all which were ſo grounded, that they could neither take nor burne them.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13473:8"/>
               <p>Three Marchants beſides, comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the 21. committed themſelues to the States fleete. So that the Spaniard loſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen great Gallions, and ſixe or ſeuen other good ſhippes beſides. The States loſt their Admirall with the firſt ſhot from the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Admirall; and among others, one cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Laughen Heyndricke</hi> of Amſterdam, and captaine <hi>Lambrechts</hi> ſonne.</p>
               <p>They haue great hurt done to their maſts, ſayles, cables, and tacklins.</p>
               <p>I Muſt further let you know, that certaine ſhippes of theſe Countries, of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany that trades to the Eaſt Indies, haue taken a very rich Carracke, which they haue lightned of her moſt precious and rich lading, and laden it into their owne ſhips, of which, one is come into Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, and the other into Zeland, and the Carracke, into which they haue put their Spices, is comming alſo.</p>
               <p>THe French Ambaſſadours are gone a progreſſe into North Holland, atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the enlarging of their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13473:9"/>
               <p>THe moſt of theſe people conceiue and feare, that the king of Spaine wil neuer ſend the Agreeation, vpon which moſt depends. <hi>Iune</hi> 16. 1607. <hi>From the Haghe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Later Newes.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are letters come from Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dä, that 2000 Spaniards are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred a backe way into the Caſtle of Antwerpe, haue turned the Artillerie vpon the Towne, and doe make warre with the Citizens. This is beleeued at the Haghe: but I will not report it for trueth, vntil the firſt be ſeconded. Farewel. From the Haghe, Iune 16. 1607.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:13473:9"/>
            <head>
               <hi>WARRES TESTAMENT,</hi> now ready to dye, after ſo long continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in the Netherlands.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THe ſickneſſe great that doth oppreſſe my hart,</l>
               <l>And cauſe each veine &amp; pulſe to pant &amp; beat,</l>
               <l>As ſignes that ſoule and body muſt depart,</l>
               <l>Do ſhew, that ſpight my heart, I cannot let</l>
               <l>The houre ta'pproch which fatal death hath ſign'd;</l>
               <l>For all things muſt returne vnto their kind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſith 'tis ſo, I then am fully bent,</l>
               <l>Before I part, for to declare my Will,</l>
               <l>And make my laſt and fatall Teſtament,</l>
               <l>And to each one, great, little, good, or ill,</l>
               <l>Bequeath my goods, and all that I poſſeſſe,</l>
               <l>And teach all theſe that Martiall Art profeſſe,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>How to deuiſe the Warres for to increaſe,</l>
               <l>And make them worſe and greater then before,</l>
               <l>And find the meanes that they ſhall neuer ceaſe,</l>
               <l>And that each countrie people, rich and poore,</l>
               <l>May feele the edge of my deuouring blade,</l>
               <l>Which in the world ſuch ſlaughter great hath made.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For though I die, and <hi>Netherlands</hi> forſake,</l>
               <l>Yet muſt you thinke, that I mine heires do leaue,</l>
               <l>That will not fayle in ought my part to take,</l>
               <l>And Countries farre and neere of peace bereaue,</l>
               <l>And make my fame, when I am dead and rotten,</l>
               <l>Still to increaſe, and neuer be forgotten.</l>
            </lg>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:13473:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>1.</head>
                  <l>Firſt I bequeath vnto the Potentate,</l>
                  <l>That many men hath brought vnto their end,</l>
                  <l>By my contentious bloudy mind and hate,</l>
                  <l>Great ſtore of goods and lands, his ſtate to mend,</l>
                  <l>And though he ſerued me with great deſire,</l>
                  <l>And rather ſought for wealth, then warre require,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And happily full many dangers paſt:</l>
                  <l>Yet let him know, what euer he hath woon,</l>
                  <l>That from it all he muſt depart at laſt,</l>
                  <l>When he his fatall courſe on earth hath runne;</l>
                  <l>And therefore counſell him for to beware,</l>
                  <l>And of his life to haue a better care.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>2.</head>
                  <l>To Tyrants great, to whom their law is will,</l>
                  <l>Who by my means much wrong &amp; hurt haue done</l>
                  <l>By falſe pretence of warre, and ſought to kill</l>
                  <l>Both man and child, and many Countries woon</l>
                  <l>By fire and ſword, conſuming townes and towers,</l>
                  <l>And wrongfully deſtroyed pleaſant Bowers,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I doe bequeath <hi>Kains</hi> curſe and baniſhment,</l>
                  <l>And though their fame b'extold vnto the aire,</l>
                  <l>Yet ſhall their hearts and minds be diſcontent,</l>
                  <l>And filled with confuſion and deſpaire,</l>
                  <l>And at the laſt with woe and miſerie,</l>
                  <l>Their bodies ſhall with lice conſumed be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>3.</head>
                  <l>To thoſe that haue bin valiant, ſtout and bold,</l>
                  <l>T'aduenture life and limme for to defend</l>
                  <l>Their Countries cauſe, and it from dangers hold,</l>
                  <l>And haue continued true vnto the end,</l>
                  <l>Offered no wrong, nor vſed villanie,</l>
                  <l>But with their pay themſelues did ſatisfie,</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13473:10"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>I cannot chuſe but wiſh them well in heart,</l>
                  <l>And praiſe and honor leaue them for their meed,</l>
                  <l>And when that they out of this world ſhall part,</l>
                  <l>Deſire of God to helpe them in their need,</l>
                  <l>And giue them conſtant faith for to perſeuer,</l>
                  <l>In godly life to liue with him for euer.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <head>4.</head>
                  <l>To Spirituall men, that are of carefull mind,</l>
                  <l>To preach and teach, I cannot leaue them much,</l>
                  <l>And they do know, and well by proofe do find,</l>
                  <l>Their Cloiſters ſpoild, whereat they ſeeme to grutch,</l>
                  <l>Their Churches burnt, their liuing ta'ne away,</l>
                  <l>And which is more, where they haue ſeen the day,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>That all their Sellers ſtored were with drinke,</l>
                  <l>Their Barnes full, their Kitchins fraught with meat,</l>
                  <l>And all things els what euer heart could thinke,</l>
                  <l>Were in their Houſes found, now nought to get,</l>
                  <l>And they poore Prieſts &amp; Couents without land,</l>
                  <l>To other mens reuerſions forc't to ſtand.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>5.</head>
                  <l>Vnto the Townes in <hi>Netherlands</hi> ſo great,</l>
                  <l>I do bequeath and leaue a great Exciſe,</l>
                  <l>And many Impoſitions that are ſet</l>
                  <l>Vpon them, though they rather would deuiſe</l>
                  <l>The meanes to liue in peace and quiet ſtate,</l>
                  <l>And thinke themſelues to be moſt fortunate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Meane time they muſt behold their raſed walles,</l>
                  <l>Their Towers caſt downe, vncouered and defac't,</l>
                  <l>Their Houſes burnt, their Palaces and Halles</l>
                  <l>Euen with the ground: for what can euer laſt,</l>
                  <l>But muſt of force conſume and eke decay?</l>
                  <l>For in this world there is no certaine ſtay.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13473:11"/>
               <lg n="6">
                  <head>6.</head>
                  <l>Vnto the countrie Village and the Towne,</l>
                  <l>I do bequeath a deſolate eſtate,</l>
                  <l>And vncoth ſight of Caſtlis, broken downe,</l>
                  <l>And houſes ſpoylde, which warre vnfortunate</l>
                  <l>Hath cauſde and made full many a man to bee</l>
                  <l>Amazed lore ſuch wofull ſights to ſee:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I leaue them Sluces fallne vnto decay,</l>
                  <l>Great ſtore of lame and miſerable folke,</l>
                  <l>Murthers committed 'mongſt them night and day,</l>
                  <l>Women deflowrde, and men brought vnder yoke</l>
                  <l>Of euery rauening freebooter and ſlaue,</l>
                  <l>To take from them what euer that they haue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <head>7.</head>
                  <l>To thoſe that by diſſention and by ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>Deceit and ſubtiltie haue gotten wealth,</l>
                  <l>And all the dayes of their vnhappie life,</l>
                  <l>Haue liu'd by couſinage, and by ſecret ſtealth,</l>
                  <l>Gathering great ſtore of riches and of good,</l>
                  <l>And neuer ceaſe to ſucke the poore mans blood,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And Vſurers, and ſuch as liue by gaine,</l>
                  <l>And ſweate of others browes, and haue no care,</l>
                  <l>But onely how to get, and to attaine</l>
                  <l>To ſpeedy wealth, to them I will not ſpare</l>
                  <l>To tell them, that all gayne by them ſo got,</l>
                  <l>With them at laſt will be the diuels lot.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="8">
                  <head>8.</head>
                  <l>You Clarks that liued by my warlike bands,</l>
                  <l>And were accounted 'mongſt the Martial crue,</l>
                  <l>And yet ne're vſed weapons in your hands,</l>
                  <l>But ſerued for to pay the Souldiers due,</l>
                  <l>And lay with them where euer they did goe,</l>
                  <l>Let me but tell you ſome that I know:</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13473:11"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>I doubt, if that I once be dead and rotten,</l>
                  <l>You will be glad to worke and take ſome paine,</l>
                  <l>And thinke a penny that way ſweetly gotten,</l>
                  <l>Though now by idleneſſe you make your gainet</l>
                  <l>Remember what I ſay, and pray that I</l>
                  <l>May liue, and make you rich before I die.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="9">
                  <head>9.</head>
                  <l>You Oſtes, that wonted were to lodge my train,</l>
                  <l>And did prepare them meat and drinke with ſpeed,</l>
                  <l>At ſuch exceſsiue rates, and monſtrous gaine,</l>
                  <l>As't pleaſed you, reſpecting not their need,</l>
                  <l>And ſo did fill your coffers and your bags,</l>
                  <l>And made the Souldiers go in tornerags,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I you bequeath a beggerly eſtate,</l>
                  <l>And to be payd by gentle words and blowes,</l>
                  <l>And thinke your ſelues well vſde and fortunate,</l>
                  <l>To ſcape ſo well, and as the world well knowes,</l>
                  <l>Be glad to ebbe and flow as time fals out,</l>
                  <l>And many times be forſt to play bankerour.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="10">
                  <head>10.</head>
                  <l>To Armorers and Spurriers by their Art,</l>
                  <l>Gunpowder men, and Sadlers that do liue</l>
                  <l>By me and mine, and get the greateſt part</l>
                  <l>Of all their wealth, a Legacie Ile giue,</l>
                  <l>Which after my deceaſe with preſent ſpeed,</l>
                  <l>Shall be payd them at the caſtle of Saint <hi>Need:</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Although I know they haue great ſtore of wealth,</l>
                  <l>Which eaſily into their cofers came,</l>
                  <l>By buying goods that gotten were by ſtealth,</l>
                  <l>And gaue but eaſie prices for the ſame.</l>
                  <l>But let them know, goods by that meanes ſo won,</l>
                  <l>Conſume and melt like butter in the Sunne.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13473:12"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:13473:12"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:13473:13"/>
               <lg n="16">
                  <head>16.</head>
                  <l>Your Horſemens boyes, Dead paies, &amp; Billet men,</l>
                  <l>All call &amp; cry to me for ſome reliefe:</l>
                  <l>For by my meanes they liu'd and knew both when</l>
                  <l>And where to get their meat: but now with griefe:</l>
                  <l>They muſt go ſeeke to make ſome other ſhift,</l>
                  <l>Or els go ſteale to helpe them at a lift.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The houſe of ſeldome full muſt be their Inne,</l>
                  <l>And if they leaue not off their villany,</l>
                  <l>The gallie, gallowes, priſon or ſome ginne</l>
                  <l>Will be their laſt reward for knaucrie:</l>
                  <l>Therefore beware in time, and learne to thriue,</l>
                  <l>And ſeeke ſome honeſt meanes for you to liue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="17">
                  <head>17.</head>
                  <l>You filthy ſhameles Drabs, that long haue thri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen</l>
                  <l>Vnder the guard of my moſt warlike traine,</l>
                  <l>And by your beaſtly liues, haue forſt and driuen</l>
                  <l>Full many a man to liue in griefe and paine,</l>
                  <l>And in the end, when all from him had gotten,</l>
                  <l>Haue fil'd him with diſeaſe to make him rotten,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Conuert in time, ere that it be too late,</l>
                  <l>Take better courſe, and now liue honeſtly,</l>
                  <l>And call for grace, while you are in the ſtate</l>
                  <l>To get the ſame, leſt graceleſſe you ſhould dye:</l>
                  <l>And follow <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> in this,</l>
                  <l>Mercy to craue, confeſsing your amiſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="18">
                  <head>18.</head>
                  <l>Laſtly vnto the Hangman I bequeath</l>
                  <l>An hundred paire of breeches that be old,</l>
                  <l>Well fil'd with lice, aboue and eke beneath,</l>
                  <l>For that ere it be long, you ſhall behold</l>
                  <l>Great ſtore of theeues, alongſt the high way ſtand</l>
                  <l>To aske your almes with weapons in their hand:</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13473:13"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>And rather then they will denyed be,</l>
                  <l>They'le be ſo bold to venture (by your leaue)</l>
                  <l>To put you to the worſt extremitie,</l>
                  <l>And take your purſe by force out of your ſleeue:</l>
                  <l>But for reward, I will them plainely ſhew,</l>
                  <l>That to the gallowes they are ſure to goe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now all at once thanke me for my good will,</l>
                  <l>And euery man in ſeuerall wiſe apart.</l>
                  <l>My courſe is runne, I muſt Gods heſts fulfill,</l>
                  <l>For I am ſicke, euen at the very heart,</l>
                  <l>I fall to ground, like to the Cripple lame,</l>
                  <l>And muſt returne to place from whence I came.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Watch now and pray, attend me but a while,</l>
                  <l>And I'le bid you adiew, for I muſt die.</l>
                  <l>When I am dead, yet do me not reuile:</l>
                  <l>For though that I haue cauſ'd much miſerie,</l>
                  <l>I'le pray to God, and while I liue, not ceaſe,</l>
                  <l>To ſend to you a long and happy peace.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
